Guide to the Grover Sales Collection ARS.0016
Archive of Recorded Sound
Grover Sales Collection
1940-2004
ARS.0016
Archive of Recorded Sound
8.0 box(es)
Sales, Grover, Mr.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into 6 series: 1. Media; 2. Writings; 3. Photographs; 4. Publications; 5. Books; 6. Miscellaneous.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists of 2018 slides of jazz musicians; jazz documentaries and interviews with famous jazz musicians on audio tapes; a well-written and entertaining autobiography; course syllabi; two articles and miscellaneous typescripts by Sales; and writings about him.
Biographical/Historical note
Grover Sales was born in Louisville, Kentucky in 1920. After serving in the Army Air Corps in Southeast Asia during World War II he studied at Reed College, Portland, Oregon and later at the University of California, Berkeley, where he received his BA in history. In his fifty-year career as a jazz critic he was known for his strongly opinionated and literate writing. Sales also wrote about film and cultural politics. His books include Jazz: America's Classical Music, a biography of John Maher, and the very successful book he co-authored with his wife, The Clay-Pot Cookbook. He taught jazz history for several years at Stanford University, San Francisco State University, the San Francisco Conservatory, and the Jazz school. Sales also worked as the publicist for the Monterey Jazz Festival from 1958 to 1965. Grover Sales died in 2004.
Access Restrictions:
Collection is open for research. Listening appointments may require 24 hours notice. Contact the Archive Operations Manager.
Jazz; Jazz musicians--Portraits
Container List
- Media
  - Slides
    - Jazz history slides (Box 1, Folder 11200)
      Scope and Contents note
      (Box 1) 1-199 -- (Box 2) 200-400 -- (Box 3) 401-600 -- (Box 4) 601-800 --(Box 5) 801-1000 -- (Box 6) 1001-1200
    - Jazz history slides (Box 2, Folder 1.2012018E7)
      (Box 7) 1201-1400 -- (Box 8) 1401-1600 -- (Box 9) 1601-1800 -- (Box 10) 1801-1990 -- (Box 11) 1992-2018
  - Videocassettes
    - Jazz on Film, VHS (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Great Day in Harlem (1994); Arlen, Harold, 1905-1986 (1999); Last of Blue Devils (1979); Pygmalion (1938)
    - Swing, swing, swing, 1999; VHS (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Krupa, Gene, 1909-1973
    - Montreal Jazz Festival, VHS (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Gillespie, Dizzy, 1917-1993; Jordan, Stanley
    - My dinner with Dizzy, VHS (Box 3, Folder 4)
      My dinner with Dizzy -- Gaillard, Slim. Civilisation (Part III). Arena BBC (1988)
      Gillespie, Dizzy, 1917-1993
    - Sound of Jazz, VHS (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Jazz and Big Band from the 30s and 40s
    - Wonderful World of Louis Armstrong, VHS (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Omnibus. BBC
      Armstrong, Louis, 1901-1971
    - South Bank. Boogie-Woogie, VHS (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Johnson, Pete, 1904-1967; Lewis, Lux, 1901-1964
    - PBS Documentary, The Choir. Episode 3; Bravo., VHS (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Marsalis, Wynton, 1961-
    - Midwest Territory Bands, VHS (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Documentary, Citizens Dancing
    - Jazz (Mario Bauzá), VHS (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Bauzá, Mario, 1911-1993
    - Completely Cuckoo, VHS (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Kesey, Ken. One flew over the cuckoo's nest -- Documentary on book.
    - Charles Mingus. Epitaph, VHS (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Mingus, Charles, 1922-1979
    - John Coltrane Legacy, VHS (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Vaughan, Sarah, 1924-1990
    - Fats Waller. Bravo, VHS (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Waller, Fats, 1904-1943
    - Farewell (Benny Goodman), 1981; VHS (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Goodman, Benny, 1909-1986
    - Jazzman from the Gulag, 1941; VHS (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Moskow
      Rosner, Eddie, 1910-1976
    - Duke Ellington, VHS (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Ellington, Duke, 1899-1974
    - George Gershwin, Beta (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Gershwin, George, 1898-1937
    - Coltrane Legacy, Beta (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Music in Monk Time. Thelonious Sphere Monk: a retrospective tribute, Beta (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Monk, Thelonious
    - Saxophone Summit, Feb. 6, 1985; Beta (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Reel to reel film
    - Unidentified (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reel to reel tapes
    - Jazz lecture. KJAZ (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Bob Houlihan
    - Bob Houlihan KJAZ (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bob Houlihan KJAZ, July 1, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Bob Houlihan KJAZ (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - [Interview with Coleman Hawkins] (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Hawkins, Coleman
    - [Interview with Charles Mingus] (Box 5, Folder 6)
      WKCR. Columbia University, N. Y.
    - Jazz Workshop. Dixieland -- Lenny Bruce, Oct. 6, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Bruce, Lenny
    - [Interview with Ray Brown, I] (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Brown, Ray, 1946-
    - [Interview with Ray Brown, II] (Box 5, Folder 9)
      On bass playing
    - [Interview with Ray Brown, III] (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - [Grover Sales interviews Joe Venuti] (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Sales, Grover, Mr.
    - Trilogy. Part I (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Sinatra, Frank, 1915-1998
    - Trilogy. Part II (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - [Bud Abbott and Lou Costello] (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Myerson Alan, director of the committee in San Francisco
      Abbott, Bud, 1895-1974; Costello, Lou
    - [Grover Sales interviews Earl Hines] (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Hines, Earl, 1903-1983
    - [Billie Holiday] (Box 6, Folder 16)
      Holiday, Billie, 1915-1959
  - Audiocassettes
    - Dylan on Dylan (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Dylan, Bob, 1941-
    - [Interview with Coleman Hawkins] (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - [Radio interview with Art Tatum], 1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Tatum, Art, 1909-1956
    - [Studs Terkel interviews Bud Freeman] (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Bud Freeman, 1906-1991; Terkel, Studs, 1912-2008
    - [Interview with Bill Evans], Nov. 1, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Evans, Bill, 1929-1980
    - [Billie Holiday speaks and performs] (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Bach dancing, Feb. 23, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      CD Master. Waltz for Debby -- Sareen Jurer -- Very early -- Autumn leaves -- What are you doing the rest -- Quiet now -- Who can I turn to -- Elsa -- Someday my Prince will come
    - [Bob Houlihan and Grover Sales talk on Blues. KJAZ] (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Young, Lester, 1909-1959; Cole, Nat King, 1917-1965; Rich, Buddy, 1917-1987 -- Houlihan broadcast. Spanier, Muggsy, 1906-1967; Russell, Pee Wee; Jackson, Cliff (1946) -- Grover Sales lecture on the Blues
      Houlihan, Bob; Sales, Grover, Mr.
    - [Jessica Williams concert and interview with Terry Gross. Part I] (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Gross, Terry; Williams, Jessica, pianist
    - [Jessica Williams concert and interview with Terry Gross. Part II] (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - [Coleman Hawkins on Jack T.] (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Spoon. "Touch"
    - John Hammond on CBC (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Grover Sales. Black Olympian (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - [Radio broadcast on the late Irene Kral with John Detro], Nov. 8, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      Detro, John; Kral, Irene
    - NPR'S Jazz Profiles: Carmen McRae with Joan Merrill, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 15)
      McRae, Carmen; Merrill, Joan
    - NPR's Jazz Profiles: Anita O'Day with Joan Merrill, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      Merrill, Joan; O'Day, Anita
    - Piano Jazz: Interview with Teddy Wilson, May 1979 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      McPartland, Marian; Wilson, Teddy, 1912-1986
    - Piano Jazz: Interview with Mary Lou Williams, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      McPartland, Marian; Williams, Mary Lou, 1910-1981
    - Piano Jazz: Interview with Susan Muscarella. KCSM, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      McPartland, Marian; Muscarella, Susan
    - Jim Easton Show: Interview with Grover Sales. KGO Radio (Box 7, Folder 20)
      Social commentary
    - Interview with Duke Ellington. KALW Radio (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Hot Summer Dance, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - First Take (Box 7, Folder 23)
      Brad Terry, clarinet; Smith Dobson, piano. Night and day; Everything happens to me; You stepped out of a dream; Midnight sun; Straighten up and fly right; But not for me; Autumn in New York; Sun's going to shine; Desifinado
      Cash, Dick; Dobson, Smith; Terry, Brad
    - New Orleans Jazz, April 1950 (Box 7, Folder 24)
      Louis Armstrong, trumpet, voice; Jack Teagarden, trombone; Earl Hines, piano
      Armstrong, Louis, 1901-1971; Hines, Earl, 1903-1983; Teagarden, Jack, 1905-1964
    - US Savings Bonds and the Mutual Broadcasting Network, Nov. 28, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 25)
      Bruce Elliott, announcer; Rudy Blesh and Barry Ulanov, commentators.
      Blesh, Rudi, 1899-1985; Elliott, Bruce; Ulanov, Barry
- Writings
  - Autobiographical
    - Ragtime Cowboy Jew (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Typescripts
    - Miscellaneous writings on the history of Jazz (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - I remember Duke (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Article for the San Francisco Chronicle
    - Jazz piano biographies for Warner new media (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Jazz piano: from Ragtime to Bebop (Box 8, Folder 4)
      First draft
  - Course syllabi
    - Stanford Continuing Studies. Survey of Jazz Syllabi. 1994, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Sales' writings
    - Clippings and magazines from 1959-2003 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Writings about Grover Sales
    - Clippings 1978-97 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clippings
    - General Clippings 1961-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    - Miscellaneous photographs and postcards (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Postcards; Grover Sales; Duke Ellington; West Coast Jazz Box; Jabbo Smith; Weston Randy
      Ellington, Duke, 1899-1974; Smith, Jabbo, 1908-1991; Weston, Randy, 1926-
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous photographs and postcards (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Postcards; Grover Sales; Ellington, Duke; West Coast Jazz Box; Smith, Jabbo; Weston Randy
- Publications
  - Monterey Jazz Festival, 1966 and 1967 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Centennial Jazz Festival, Apr. 19-20, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Second Annual U.C. Jazz Festival
  - American Mavericks, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    A look at 20th century music in the United States from the San Francisco Symphony
- Books
  - Sales, Grover. John Maher of Delancey Street, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Maher, John, 1940-
- Miscellaneous
  - Unidentified piano roll (Box 8, Folder 1)